Hi! My name is Shadi Abou-Zahra.
أهلا! اسمي شادي أبو زهرة.‪
I'm the Accessibility Strategy and Technology Specialist at W3C,
أنا إختصاصي في استراتيجية وتكنولوجيا الولوجيات عند W3C،
the World Wide Web Consortium,
مَجمَع شبكة الويب العالمية،
and today I'd like to tell you about web accessibility.
واليوم أود أن أتحدث معك حول إمكانية الولوج إلى الويب.
The Web is for many people an essential part of daily life.
الويب هو جزء أساسي من الحياة اليومية للكثير من الأشخاص.
At work.
في العمل.
At home.
في البيت.
And on the road.
وعلى تحرك.
Web accessibility means that people with disabilities can use the Web equally.
ولوجية الويب، اوإمكانية الوصول إلى الويب ، تعني أنه في إمكان الأشخاص ذوي الإعاقات استخدام الويب مثل أي شخص آخر.
For example, somebody who cannot use their arms, and uses a mouthstick to type.
على سبيل المثال، شخص لا يملك استخدام ذراعيه ويستخدم مقبض للكتابة بالفم.
Or someone who cannot hear well, and uses captions to watch videos.
أو شخص  لا يسمع جيدا يستخدم الترجمات لمشاهدة أشرطة الفيديو.
Or someone who cannot see well, and uses a screen reader to read aloud what's on the screen.
شخص لا يرى جيدا يستخدم قارئ الشاشة لنطق ما يحدث على الشاشة بصوت عال.
Accessibility has many benefits.
للولوجيات فوائد عديدة.
For example, captions benefit anyone in a loud or in a quiet environment.
على سبيل المثال، الترجمات تفيد أي شخص في محيط ضاج أو في محيط هادئ.
And good color contrast works better when there is glare.
وتباين الألوان جيد هوأفضل في حالة الضوء الساطع.
Also people with age-related impairments, such as reduced dexterity, benefit.
يستفيد أيضا الشخص الذي يعاني من تدهور مرتبط بالسن، مثل الانخفاض  في البراعة.
In fact, everyone has a better user experience with an improved layout and design.
في الواقع،  تصميم ونصق أحسن يعزز تجربة مستخدم  للجميع.
A lot of accessibility can be built into the underlying code of websites and applications.
يمكن إنشاء الكثير من الولوجيات في الشفرة الأساسية لمواقع الويب والتطبيقات.
Web technologies from W3C, such as HTML, provide support for many accessibility features.
تكنولوجيات الويب لدى W3C، مثل HTML، تراعي للعديد من ميزات الولوجيات.
For example, features to provide text alternatives for images,
على سبيل المثال، ميزات لتوفير نص بديل للصور،
which are read aloud by screen readers and also used by search engines.
والذي  يتم نطقه بصوت عال من قبل قراء الشاشة، ويستخدم أيضا من قبل محركات البحث.
Also headings, labels, and other code supports accessibility
كما أن العناوين والتسميات وغيرها من العلامات تراعي للولوجية
and improves the quality overall.
وتحسن الجودة الشاملة.
Good authoring tools, such as wikis, content management systems, and code editors,
أدوات التأليف الجيدة، مثل الويكي وإدارة المحتوى، وتحرير الشفرات،
help create accessible code, either automatically or with input from the author.
تساعد على إنشاء شفرة ولوجية بشكل تلقائي أو بمساهمة المؤلف.
Also web browsers, media players, and apps need to support accessibility features.
كما يجب على متصفحات الويب ومشغلات الوسائط والتطبيقات مراعاة ميزات الولوجية.
W3C provides standards to help make the Web accessible,
‏W3C يوفر معايير ليساعد في جعل الويب ولوجي،
which are internationally recognized by governments and businesses.
و التي هي معترف بها دوليا من طرف الحكومات والشركات.
Most well-known is the Web Content Accessibility Guidelines - WCAG.
والأكثر شهرة هي المبادئ التوجيهية لولوجية محتوى الويب - WCAG.
WCAG is also the ISO standard 40500,
و هي أيضا معيار ISO رقم 40500،
and adopted in the European standard called EN 301 549.
واعتمدت في المعيار الأوروبي المسمىِ EN 301 549.
It is built around four core principles:
وهي  مبنية على أربعة مبادئ رئيسية :
First Perceivable - for example, so people can see the content, or hear it.
أولا الإسْتيعاب. يجب القدرة على رؤية المحتوى أو السماع اليه مثلا.
Operable - for example, so people can use the computer by typing, or by voice.
وقابلية التشغيل. يمكن استخدام الكمبيوتر عن طريق لوحة المفاتيح أو عن طريق الصوت مثلا.
Understandable - for example, so people get clear and simple language.
ويمكن فهمه. يجب استعمال أسلوب واضح وبسيط مثلا.
And Robust - so people can use different assistive technologies.
وقوي. حتى نتمكن من استخدام مختلف تقنيات المساعدة.
Besides WCAG, W3C also provides the Authoring Tool Accessibility Guidelines - ATAG,
بالإضافة إلى WCAG، يوفر W3C أيضا المبادئ التوجيهية  لولوجية أدوات التأليف - ATAG،
which defines requirements for content management systems, code editors and other software.
التي تحدد المتطلبات لأنظمة إدارة المحتوى، وتحرير الشفرات وغيرها من البرامج.
And the User Agent Accessibility Guidelines - UAAG,
والمبادئ التوجيهية  لولوجية عميل المستخدم - UAAG
defines requirements for web browsers and media players.
تحدد المتطلبات لمتصفحات الويب ومشغلات الوسائط.
There are over one billion people with disabilities, or about 15-20% of the population.
هناك أكثر من مليار شخص  لديهم إعاقة، أو حوالي 15-20٪ من السكان.
The UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities
اتفاقية الأمم المتحدة لحقوق الأشخاص ذوي الإعاقة
defines that access to information, including the Web, as a human right.
تنص على أن الوصول إلى المعلومة، بما في ذلك شبكة الويب، هو حق من حقوق الإنسان.
Most countries around the world have ratified this UN convention,
وقد صادقت معظم بلدان العالم على اتفاقية الأمم المتحدة هذه،
and several have adopted binding policies too.
واعتمد العديد منهم سياسات ملزمة في هذا الشأن.
Yet regardless of any laws and regulations,
وبغض النظر عن أي قوانين ومراسيم،
implementing the accessibility standards is essential for people with disabilities,
فإن إدراج معايير الولوجيات هو أمر أساسي للأشخاص ذوي الإعاقة،
and useful for all.
وهو مفيد للجميع.
For more information on web accessibility, visit w3.org/WAI
لمزيد من المعلومات حول ولوجيات الويب، قم بزيارة الموقع w3.org/WAI